hello everyone this is Frank D Freitas
and welcome to a brand new season of
hollow talk for the
1999-2000 season this show is for the
week of September 13 1999 and this is
the third season of whole talk that
we're going into I'd like to extend a
welcome to my regular listeners who are
coming back for another season but I'd
also like to send out a special Welcome
to our new listeners who are listening
to hollow talk for the first time
so if you're a new listener I'd like to
welcome you aboard and I hope you enjoy
the upcoming season and I'll tell you a
little bit about what whole talk is
about
um the whole talk gives us an
opportunity to chat with guests on a
regular basis who work with lasers and
Holograms and it also gives the
listeners an opportunity to sit back and
relax and keep in touch
with what's happening in the field of
lasers and Holograms that's the field
that we know in the field that we love
and
it's nice to be able to have this
opportunity to come into your schools
your homes and your offices and bring
this information to you
so I hope you come back and check out
these shows that will be coming up
during the season the season runs from
Labor Day to Memorial Day and then we're
off for the summer
and speaking of Summers I hope everyone
had a great summer I had a pretty good
summer we did a lot of exciting things
around here in the lab that I'm going to
get to in a few minutes but one of the
memories of this summer is the extreme
extreme heat that just blanketed the
entire Northeast part of the country and
Pennsylvania in particular
this County that Allentown is located in
which is Lehigh County is one of three
counties in the state where the farmers
had to declare 100 percent crop loss
it was a very very sad sight to be
driving around and seeing the crops and
corn for instance only grew about to the
height of someone's calf on your leg I
don't even think it would even reach
your knees that's if it grew at all as
you would drive around on the different
highways in the turnpike you would see
the corn fields and there were entire
areas where the corn never even sprouted
or came up it was just bald baked Earth
and this went on for weeks and weeks and
weeks and the only thing that you could
do would be just to sit back stay in the
shade and hope to survive which
unfortunately there were a number of
people who didn't survive this extreme
heat
but that's all over now outside the
whole talk Studio it's a very calm
cool evening and after I finished this
show I think I'm going to go out and sit
out back and listen to what's left of
the crickets for the season as the
temperature continues to drop and we
move into the fall once again and give
up our summer activities for those
activities in the fall and winter which
includes a lot of work indoors and
hopefully for the whole talk listeners
back into the lab to begin our
experiments with the great field of
holography
I kept going back and forth on whether I
should increase the quality of the
broadcast of whole talk I certainly have
the equipment here in the studio to do
some very high quality Broadcasting
of course anytime you send out a show
which is very high quality you have to
have people who have the capability of
receiving that information which means
some modems that are at least 28 8 or
higher 56k
and I kept coming back to the picture of
this
little boy or little girl
out somewhere in the middle of America
or maybe south east south west that you
know money's a little tight in the house
and the kids got a computer it's not a
great computer it may be a computer that
maybe is uh his or her uncle gave them
for
a birthday present they hand me down and
it's got this 14-4 modem attached to it
and there's certainly
if there was going to be a purchase made
in that household it would probably be
for sneakers or clothes it certainly
wouldn't be a new modem for the computer
so
I see this kid sitting in the bedroom
with the computer and
they like holography they like lasers
and
they enjoy listening to the whole talk
show and
I keep thinking what a shame it would be
that if I were to make this show where
it would only be available to someone
with a 28 8 or a 56k modem even though
that would increase the quality of the
show you would really hear some of the
capabilities of the quality Equipment
here in the studio
all of a sudden they would log on for
the show and the next thing you know it
would say you know we're sorry you can't
receive this information your modem
isn't fast enough and what a shame that
would be so
I decided to just keep it at the regular
rate that I normally broadcast for the
past two season which is uh 8.5 kilobits
per second which allows anyone with a
14-4 modem to pick up the show
and if you're one of those people out
there my friend my little friend or
friends there's probably many of you
this is for you so that you can continue
to listen to the show and follow the
field of holography
maybe even start making some holograms
on your own and who knows where that
will lead you
so that's the reason why the show is
still coming through at the same rate
that it's been coming through for the
past two seasons it's not anything to do
with what we're capable of doing it's
more
to do with the fact that we do have some
little ones out there that listen to
this show and I think it's very
important that if they do like this
that they're able to get the information
uh something that's new for all of you
if you happen to have real player plus
which is
um
the 5.0 version or the 4.0 version or
even even a new G2 a real player you'll
be able to put holotalk as one of your
favorites sort of like a bookmark or one
of the uh
that presets that you have on a regular
radio if you have the plus series of
these players you have the capability of
doing that when you go to a website and
you listen to a show
you're able to click on your favorites
and that'll become a button right on
your real player
this gives you the advantage of not
having to log on to the website to
listen to the show each week is say for
instance you listen to the show on a
Tuesday night
sit back with your cup of coffee or a
Darjeeling tea
and enjoy a hollow talk now you don't
need to log on to the website go to the
webpage click on the link and have real
player launch just get your milk layer
up
and click on the favorite button it
should say Holo talk right on the button
if you choose it as a favorite and each
week's show will begin to play
automatically for you so that's a little
feature that we're going to do that we
didn't have for the past two seasons so
that sort of might make up for the fact
that I didn't increase the quality of
the show but I increased the
uh the absolute the quality of the
delivery on how you can receive it so a
little bit of a trade-off there
well I've got a great lineup of guests
this season I'm not going to get into
who the guests are I know last season I
sort of uh made a list of who was going
to be on and when they were going to be
on but unfortunately uh I mean this is
this is the whole talk show and most of
the people who work in the field of
holography have businesses and they
travel and they do different things and
different things come up at the last
moment and even though we did get most
of the guests on they certainly weren't
on the same week I had to do a little
bit of a scrambled eggs things there
where I took one person put them changed
them another week and changed someone
else around so I'm not going to go into
uh what dates each of the guests and
things are going to be on but I would
recommend that you get on the mailing
list and I have the whole talk mailing
list if you go to my email page or maybe
I'll even have a link right on the whole
talk page for you if you get on the
mailing list each week you'll receive
one email a short email it's nothing
like a junk mail that's coming into your
email box every day your email address
never ever goes out for any other
purpose except right on my machine for
holotalk and I'll send you an email and
let you know a reminder because we all
forget sometimes uh that uh you know
whole talks coming up this week and this
is the guess and this is what the
Topic's going to be so tune in I'll give
you a little bit of a reminder to come
back and listen to the show so get on
the mailing list and see what the shows
are going to be each week you may not
have an interest in some of the shows
but some of them might hit a nail right
on the head for you as far as interest
so you don't want to miss that
well as many of you know
I take the summer off from Memorial day
until Labor Day and especially with the
website and holography and by the way I
will be updating the website on a
regular basis I've got a number of
different updates that are going to go
on there so you want to keep coming back
as the weeks go on and see some of the
new things that go up
but there was still a lot of activity
around the lab
the biggest news is that you may
remember at the end of last season we
were really trying to get a
35 milliwatt diode
together you know to run our own design
which means that our own driver power
supply and with a purchase diode and you
know we just worked and I say we I'm
talking as Sam Savage is a friend of
mine who's been coming in and working
with this uh he's from New Jersey and uh
we've been going back and forth and I'll
tell you something we just ripped our
hair out trying to
improve the performance of some of these
diodes and come up with a laser that
really has incredible specifications
well right before we got ready to do
Holo talk in fact within the last week
I'd say going back maybe seven to ten
days
we finally got it we built the entire
system and let me tell you something
folks this is an incredible laser and
hopefully I'll have a link onto the site
where you can go in and take a look at
the laser and some of the things that
we've done and we're going to have to
get the power supply and the driver size
down a little bit and things but we're
basically going to make this into a
self-contained laser where you would
just sit on your holography table and
have quite a bit of power to work with
at a very affordable price and we'll
also have plans that you can get on how
to build your own that you're handy with
a soldering gun and a circuit board
there's a number of different components
involved with it but it's nothing like
building your own computer or anything
with the boards and things so
certainly within the realm of most
hobbyists to be able to sit down and
solder these things together
it very very impressive work who did a
beautiful hologram as the test shot and
right now I'm working on setting up to
do a nice eight by ten and if we see
good results which I am expecting to see
and move up to 30 by 40 centimeter
plates which are rather large Holograms
you're getting up into a display size
you know where you can show in a gallery
or you know a Lobby or whatever you know
but what's really nice the The Fringe
stability this this is what we were
really trying to work out you know we
put a couple of the different laser
pointers and a couple of the different
diodes on uh set up an interferometer
and took a look at the fringes and I'll
tell you what once you have these diodes
hooked up to an interferometer they
they're a little squirrely they're
actually a little squirrely so what we
wanted to do is we wanted to come up
with a laser that would have extreme
stability and the way to do this
actually was through the uh
the electronics so and this is the area
that sand shines in we tried a number of
different things over the summer and all
of them failed and you know I'm like
here depressed like Beyond
depression you know because things pop
the diode or we'd never be able to get
the fringes the way that we want them
and then he'd you know get the circuit
board back and start working with
different things and trying different
chips and you know I'm not an
Electronics guy so I'm not
really capable of sitting here and
telling you the electronic end of this
but we will have Sam come on and tell
you know the story behind this which is
a pretty fascinating story on how this
was done
so I've had this uh running for about 10
days 24 hours a day I've got it hooked
up to an interferometer on the table and
we're watching the fringes and I want to
tell you something I have never seen
fringes so tight very high contrast
fringes that are so absolutely still it
looks like
Fringe Locker is uh in place on the
table
and I've never seen it in any fringes
that look this still with a gas laser
and I've had some nice gas lasers here
like my spectrophysics stabilite 124b
which was a very good laser in its time
but and also some other regular tube
lasers of cylindrical housing with the
brick power supplies
and you look them up to a near barometer
and you take a look at them and and this
fringes are relatively uh stable but you
do notice drift
and it's what I call float and and Float
is even though the fringes are still
there's some sort of float to them all
the time with a gas laser it just has
this feeling even though the eyes can't
detect it I think the mind is still
picking it up or it's more of a feeling
that uh
just sort of a light float to that to
the fringes over time but with this
diode these things these fringes are so
still that a number of times I just go
over and tap on the table just to make
sure that um
things are working okay because I've
never seen fringes like this before I
mean these things are really locked in
tight and it's a pink sand design some
sort of a closed loop feedback or
something so that the diode can monitor
itself
the laser diode can monitor itself and
it makes very quick micro changes and
current and or voltage or something like
that to make absolutely certain that it
remains stable
and I for whatever this is worth I don't
know what this means of for whatever
it's worth I went over a little earlier
and I was just watching the voltage
output to the diode and it was
absolutely locked in down to a
thousandth of a volt it didn't even
change and I imagine the current is uh
also locked in like that as well so that
that's a very good indication of some
very stable output
what's really interesting about this all
this is I wanted to get some sort of an
idea of what the coherence length is and
if you're a new listener or a new person
to holography the coherence length and
some indication of how deep
the image can be in your hologram and if
you exceed the coherence length of your
laser everything beyond that coherence
length is not going to record high
contrast fringes in your Emulsion your
recording medium your plates or your
film
and it will not show up in the Hologram
which you normally get using a helium
neon laser is you just watch the image
as it dims out rather quickly and then
becomes black from that area back
I set up this interferometer and I
stopped
at 14 feet which I believe works out to
about 4.5 meters but 14 feet was where I
stopped on the coherence line at the end
I did not notice any change in The
Fringe contrast at all I was using the
science and mechanics photometer to take
the probe into the light and dark areas
of the fringes to compare those two
readings and come up with a fringe
contrast ratio
and it's like well I'll tell you what
I'm not going to spend any more time on
this because if a holographer can get 14
feet of coherence length minimum this
isn't maximum this isn't the end of the
line at all
the minimum amount of coherence line for
that 14 feet
will you need any more I mean to get
that type of coherence length with any
traditional lab laser you usually have
to add a rather expensive edelon into
the into the optical path to to get that
type of Fringe contrast at that distance
and as we continue to expand that we're
going to go into we're actually getting
25 milliwatts of optical output power
from the a diode that's minimum and
typical output is around 27 which is
measured exactly to what the
measurements were for the power
Technologies unit that I have here the
35 milliwatt power Technologies and I
think
one of the holographers in Norway Ronnie
Anderson also has the power technology
unit and he also records at 27
milliwatts of optical output power from
the 35 milliwatt module
so that's what we wanted to try and at
least match
so we guarantee the 25 milliwatts output
but more than likely you're going to get
26.5 or 27 milliwatts after it passes
through the optical system uh the
collimating Optics that's inside of the
housing that we have
so if everything goes as planned this is
a Saturday night right now that I'm
recording this right around midnight and
this will go up and right around
midnight on Sunday night so within the
next 24 hours if I have an opportunity
I'm going to get that web page up for
you and show you it's going to be very
raw and these are really just a soldered
circuit boards and things like that but
you'll be able to take a look at the new
laser system which is very exciting news
for everyone in holography I don't need
to tell you again after telling you so
much last season how much you would pay
to go out and buy a brand new 25
milliwatt helium Leon laser system
and this is going to give holographers
an opportunity to move up in the power
range and going along with that what
happened that you can do larger
Holograms
and display them and start doing some
very serious holographic work that you
would not have had the opportunity to do
before because of such a large cash
outlay to go into this power range
and for anyone who just wants to uh
stay with the smaller Holograms like the
four by fives or so or even the eight by
ten this translates into uh extremely
quick exposure times our exposures on
the four by fives that we were working
with was just a fraction of a second
that helps as well
so
keep tuned to the gut site for updates
on this information and hopefully when
you log on at Monday the 13th you hear
this broadcast I'll have a little link
there where you can go and check out the
pictures of the laser and I've got some
shots of the beam even a shot of Sam
Savage himself
had one of the instruments that he used
to measure the
quality of the electronic output from
the driver and power supply and we'll
have this set up so that it can be run
either AC or DC you can either plug it
in the wall and use it or you can
battery operated use it so it
it's a great it's going to be a great
little addition to the field of
holography to get this up and running
and I know we've been working on this
for a very very long time and uh it's
it's good to finally have it here and
working and everything worked out with
it it's a it's a big load off of both of
our shoulders to have been able to do
this and reach our objectives of having
a very high quality uh very stable
output that exceeds the best helium neon
lasers out there in the power range for
a fraction a fraction of the cost
so that's the news here in the lab I
can't think of anything offhand that's
bigger news than that to follow up on
but a number of smaller things in our
way fill you in on as time goes on and
the season goes on and next week we will
start with our first guest
and don't forget to log back on to enjoy
next week's show each week There's a new
show and uh also I would just like to
tell you that if you have any questions
about lasers or holography and you'd
like to have that question answered on
the air on the whole talk page you will
see a telephone number that you can call
when you call the telephone number you
will have instructions on leaving your
question
and I will go into the voicemail box
that I set up specifically for the
holography questions and take your
question out and I will answer it on the
air so if you have any questions please
call in it would be fun to hear yourself
ask the question on the show you don't
have to leave your name or where you're
calling from although if you could leave
just a first name like say hello this is
this is Pete from Minnesota
that's not going to give anyone too much
information over the Internet about Pete
in Minnesota so at least it will
personalize your question a little bit
without giving out too much information
then go ahead and ask your question
I'll extract the questions from the
voicemail and I'll set them up into the
hollow talk shows
well that about wraps it up for this
week once again welcome back welcome to
our new listeners
and I'm really looking forward to giving
you a another great season of whole talk
shows I'm just assuming that the other
seasons were great as well
and I guess I'm just about going to wrap
it up so thank you for tuning in the
next show will go up around midnight on
the 19th
yeah for the week of the 20th
and I certainly hope you come back and
log on and enjoy our first guest of the
season
and you will find out ahead of time who
that guest is if you get on the mailing
list there's no advertising in the
mailing list or anything like that it's
just a little notice that I send out on
who's going
showing what the Topic's going to be
so thank you very much for tuning in
this is Frankie Freitas
and I'll talk to you next week good
night